<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Der Joachim</title>
    <description>Weblog and personal website by Joachim van de Haterd, geek, runner, motorcyclist, father and professional know-it-all.
</description>
    <link>http://derjoachim.nl/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://derjoachim.nl/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2015 21:13:29 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2015 21:13:29 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Quarter Turn of a Single Screw</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My motorcycle had some difficulty handling, so much even that in the winter weather, I was actually uncomfortable riding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the middle of winter now and the weather is cold and harsh. If possible, I still ride. But slowly my Beemer had started to feel heavier. It took some more effort to steer it and when braking, it felt as if it first &#39;dove&#39; before any actual deceleration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a particularly slippery Thursday morning I almost fell when the car in front of me suddenly wasn&#39;t only non-stationary, but uncomfortably so. All I could do, was move sideways. The icy road did the rest and I was forced to park my Beemer on its cilinder protector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought that my front shock absorber was gone. There&#39;s no shame in that, since it is already 15 years old. Old stuff breaks, especially when regularly used. However, I remembered something from my repair manual: those clever Germans made my front shock absorber adjustable. So before going shopping, I decided to take a look first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I removed the side fairing and inspected the front shock absorber. It appeared dusty and grimy, but intact. Right on the left side, there was a screw, possibly a M6. After a quarter turn, I reinstalled the fairing and I rode off to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in my experienced hands, my Beemer suddenly appeared to jump forward upon accelerating. It handled more easily and the steering reminded me of a razor blade again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much difference for a quarter turn of a single screw...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bizarre.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2015/01/31/a-quarter-turn-of-a-single-screw</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2015/01/31/a-quarter-turn-of-a-single-screw</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>In Praise of the Blade Song</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;...or the case for traditional wet shaving&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;I must confess that I only truly discovered wet shaving some 18 months ago. I first shaved at age 15, which was in the early 90s. It used the popular two blade system of the day and shaving foam. As much as I thought it made me look manly, I hated shaving. The shaving foam was harsh on the skin and as soon as a blade got blunt, I managed to draw some blood. As soon as my beard was full enough to grow out, I stopped shaving altogether. In that respect, I am a chip off the old block. My father has had a beard for 45 years now and I have never seen him without one. It should be safe to say that I have never been truly educated in the gentlemanly art of shaving.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;During my puberty I had bad acne. I had a greasy skin and my pores clogged worse than a Taco Bell toilet. One of my aunts who was a beautician in the day told me to use a traditional shaving soap. That worked: my cheeks and chin were looking pretty good, whereas my forehead looked somewhat like Pizza the Hutt.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;I do not dislike facial hair, even if it tends to get itchy. On the contrary, it fit whatever I thought appropriate at the moment for my style. Please note that this style was inspired by the idea of not wanting to shave. However, to have a beard and not look scruffy is an art. It is not an art that I have mastered. I have experimented with sideburns (which are too much hassle to maintain), chinstraps (not good), the Van Dyke (which made me look like my evil twin) and even the dreaded soul patch, which has sadly been taken over by tacky baby boomers. I settled on the perpetual three day beard look, using electric clippers.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;Using an electric hair clipper is practical. In 10 minutes flat, you can look like a rugged traveller. There is some pesky cleaning up to do afterwards, but it is a nice tradeoff for a low maintenance look. For me, there was a disadvantage though. I have bad skin and having badly lubricated moving metal parts on your unprepared skin does not help. So I bought myself an expensive cartridge system. The irritation of my skin got somewhat better. However, as I soon found out, a three blade system does not ..um.. cut it.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;Back in 2011, I did my first head shave with a cartridge razor. It was on a vacation in the deep south of the USA. I wanted to travel as light as possible, so I did not bring the electric clippers. In the meantime, I had ‘graduated’ to a five-plus-one blade system. The shave was a hassle for two reasons: I had to get rid of two weeks of growth and a multi-blade cartridge is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a good tool for the job. However, when I was finally done, I decided that this was a good look. And in the humid heat of Louisiana, it felt really refreshing to have a shaven skull.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;The head shaves stayed, since I found a way to hide my male pattern baldness. I did have a problem though. I did not have the right tools. After all, the little hairs have the nasty habit of clogging the blades. This pissed me off very much. Cartridges are bloody expensive and they simply do not last long when you shave your head. I could toss one out after one of two shaves which in all honesty is not good at 3 to 4 euros apiece. Additionally, since the razor blades tended to clog, I wasted a needless amount of time trying to clean them, sometimes even requiring a toothpick.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;A way out of this conundrum was handed to me by one of the techie forums I visit: shave like your grandfather. Use a double edge blade or even a straight razor. Sometimes the old-fashioned way &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the better way. I bought myself a DE razor and a sample pack of blades. After &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/joachimvdhaterd/status/299616181885743105&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;announcing&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter that Slayer’s &#39;Raining Blood’ would be the theme song of the day, I had my first traditional shave.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;I got hooked. Fast. The term ‘baby bottom smooth’ got an entirely new meaning. Never have I looked (and felt) any better. My skin irritation disappeared and after buying a few traditional soaps and some additional blades, I must confess that I am hooked. What started out as a way to cope with a chore, evolved into a meditation, a way of temporarily stepping out of hectic life and taking some me-time. There is something deeply soothing into selecting a soap, whipping up a lather, choosing a razor and a blade and doing a three pass shave. Sometimes I listen to a podcast or an album I want to check out, but more often, I merely listen to the song of my razor blade. For the uninitiated, it somewhat sounds like butter being spread on toast. One can hear how smooth he is by listening to the sound of the blade on the skin. If you do not hear anything, you are as smooth as a cue ball.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;Please do not make the mistake of assuming that you will cut costs. Initially, you will. A pack of 10 blades is 2 euros, a decent soap can be bought for 1 euro and a luxury razor can be bought for 30 euros. You will need a brush and some after shave, but then you should be set.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;But then the virus hits and you start to collect stuff.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;My shaving hobby has triggered me to make a collection of soaps (11 different brands, ranging from mentholated to sandalwood and myrrh), brushes (2, must buy more), blades (18 different brands and models ranging from mild to katana-sharp), razors (three) and after shaves (8-ish, including balms). Our bathroom smells like an old time barbershop and I have gained some nice in depth knowledge into the gentlemanly art of shaving. As I love pampering myself in front of the mirror, my wife thinks I have become very strange. However, she notices that I look better. And she just loves to smell the soaps and after shaves.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;Even if I do not look that much different, I certainly feel like that. My clean-shaven look has given me a confidence boost. I feel better groomed, more like a gentleman and notice that I started dressing the part. Even a three day beard looks better on me, which is pretty strange, given that the point of all this is about getting rid of facial hair.&lt;/p&gt;



</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2014 08:39:47 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2014/11/09/in-praise-of-the-blade-song</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2014/11/09/in-praise-of-the-blade-song</guid>
        
        
        <category>ramblings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Philosophy, Architecture and Ants</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On &lt;strong&gt;29 &amp;amp; 30 October 2014&lt;/strong&gt;, the yearly-ish Nooku Jam was held. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moyoweb.nl/&quot;&gt;Moyo Web Architects&lt;/a&gt; team was there with a stronger presence than ever. As one of the organizers put it, we keep spawning. Five of us were there. Two of us did presentations and one of us tells his story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For a regular participant of the Nooku Jam, the venue was familiar: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://flandersdc.be/&quot;&gt;Flanders DC&lt;/a&gt; creativity lab in Leuven, Belgium. Conveniently located near the city center with its many restaurants and pubs, it is the ideal place to let the creativity (and coffee!) flow first and let the beer flow later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jam itself was held along its traditional &lt;a href=&quot;http://barcamp.org/w/page/405173/TheRulesOfBarCamp&quot;&gt;barcamp&lt;/a&gt; format. There was no preset agenda. Participants were encouraged to share their ideas and wishes on the Wall of Ideas&amp;trade;. A vote was cast for the favorite subjects and the ones with most votes were planned as a presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The First Day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 1 had the customary talk about the roadmap and recent changes in the framework and platform by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/johanjanssens&quot;&gt;Johan Janssens&lt;/a&gt;. He also explained about the philosophy behind Nooku. It distinguishes itself from other frameworks by being not only a framework, but rather a complete architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good tradition was held up by house philosopher &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/HermanPeeren&quot;&gt;Herman Peeren&lt;/a&gt;. This time he talked about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data,_context_and_interaction&quot;&gt;DCI&lt;/a&gt; design pattern, which is not only relatively unknown, but hardly used in any PHP framework. Of course, Nooku does support it. Johan showed us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/stevenrombauts&quot;&gt;Steven Rombauts&lt;/a&gt; did an interesting talk on Elastic Search, a Lucene-based multilingual full-text search engine. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rhcpoort&quot;&gt;Robin Poort&lt;/a&gt; discussed gruntjs and how he used it to automate repetitive development-related tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special guest this year was &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rastin&quot;&gt;Rastin Mehr&lt;/a&gt;, developer of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://getanahita.com/&quot;&gt;Anahita&lt;/a&gt; open source knowledge networking platform. He explained how his implementation was inspired by naturally occuring patterns, such as the migration of ants. His talk was quite impressive and he was awarded with the &#39;most interesting talk&#39; award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Second Day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two themes were particularly characteristic to this edition of the nooku Jam, there was much focus on mobile development and Javascript frameworks. Both were extensively covered during the second day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/janssenstom&quot;&gt;Tom Janssens&lt;/a&gt; and Robin Poort discussed the mobile first and progressive enhancement theorems. In order to support any platform and resolution, one should start from the smallest resolution and work up to the big desktop-sized resolutions. Also, one should start designing with only HTML and CSS in mind and enhance upon this basic design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, our own &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JaspervanRijbro&quot;&gt;Jasper van Rijbroek&lt;/a&gt; demonstrated one of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/JaspervRijbroek/raddish&quot;&gt;hobby projects&lt;/a&gt;: a framework written in Nodejs that follows the Nooku architecture. His talk was regarded one of the most interesting talks of the entire Jam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our developer &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Klaasvaak_&quot;&gt;Joep van der Heijden&lt;/a&gt; did a talk on emberjs and how he made it play nice with Nooku in the backend. He demonstrated it by showing off one of our projects, a frontend to a shared content repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long time Nooku contributor and former colleague &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/holeedave&quot;&gt;Dave Li&lt;/a&gt; gave a further explanation on a number of frameworks aimed at mobile development. It started as an introduction to the Ionic framework, but evolved into a comparison of several competitors. Phonegap was discussed, as well as Titanium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day two ended with the usual lightning talks on interesting apps (of which &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/peterraeves&quot;&gt;Peter Raeves&lt;/a&gt; will give an overview), a well-improvised talk by Herman Peeren on -amongst others- the first encyclopedia and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/wat&quot;&gt;reminder&lt;/a&gt; of how some programming languages misbehave by Dave Li.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Afterword&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nooku Jam ended for me with a long motorcycle ride. In order to prevent being hypnotized by the dark roads, I mulled over everything I saw and heard. It was my first Jam as a non-developer, but I would not have liked to miss this Jam. The community is awesome! Their collective knowledge, drive and love of sharing is reason enough to go. However, what I saw in terms of interesting techniques made me second guess my decision to stop developing. To borrow one of the taglines from &lt;a href=&quot;http://drupal.org&quot;&gt;A Certain Other CMS&lt;/a&gt; (and a nod to Herman Peeren), I came for the community, but stayed for the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a guest post on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://nooku.org/blog&quot;&gt;Nooku blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2014/11/03/on-philosophy-architects-and-ants</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2014/11/03/on-philosophy-architects-and-ants</guid>
        
        
        <category>ramblings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The New &#39;CARPE DIEM&#39;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a bit jealous of my one year old son. Every day he keeps discovering things that have long been trivial for the adult world. He does this with a triumphant smile and welcomes his newfound knowledge with an abundance of joy. 17 months later, the text &#39;Hello World&#39; that we sent to our friends and families appears to be spot on.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;h2&gt;Hello World&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A traditional way of starting the journey into a new programming language, is by writing a script or program that simply outputs &#39;Hello World&#39;. It was this excitement that I tried to convey to my friends and family when my son was born. I was at the start of an entirely new era, that of being a father. Therefore, instead of a cheesy rhyme, we simply put the &#39;Hello World&#39; text on a card. My developer friends and colleagues loved it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Keep Learning&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One important life lesson I learnt in the past ten years is that personal development is achieved or kept up by learning some new things every year or so. One could learn a new language (natural or programming), a new musical instrument, or a new sport. One could travel to unknown places or learn to drive a new vehicle. One must always keep reading interesting stuff. One could switch careers. The important thing is: just keep moving. Keep your body and mind occupied, lest you get rusty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Seizing the Day&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The old adage of &#39;Carpe Diem&#39; means that you should make the best of the present, because you cannot know the future. I found this to be true, but somewhat lacking. &#39;Carpe Diem&#39; is easy to abuse. One can fully live in the present without preparing oneself for the future, which I do not think that the original writer intended.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;SALVE MVNDE&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Observing my son has reminded&amp;nbsp;me of an important thing: keep discovering. There is a world out there that is too interesting to ignore. I am going to abuse the Latin language here and propose a new adage: Salve Munde, which very roughly translates as &#39;Hello World&#39;. Start new things, lest the future obsoletes the stuff&amp;nbsp;you already know. Find your pleasure in the discovery of new knowledge and share it with your loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Edit by Joachim, 18-11-2014: Salve Mund&lt;strong&gt;i&lt;/strong&gt; should actually be Salve Mund&lt;strong&gt;e&lt;/strong&gt;, since one would use the vocative case&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2014 11:55:24 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2014/10/17/why-salve-mvnde-should-be-the-new-carpe-diem</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2014/10/17/why-salve-mvnde-should-be-the-new-carpe-diem</guid>
        
        
        <category>joablog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I&#39;m Not a Diehard. I Am Merely Stubborn</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, we were experiecing a heat wave. One day, it reached its scorching peak of 35 degrees Celsius, which for a temperate sea climate is extremely hot. Along with a low humidity of ~35% and a strong wind, one could say that it may not have been the best moment to go on a run, most of all on the hottest part of the day.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;I went anyway.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;During my run, I saw a man who was eating an ice cream. Our gazes briefly locked as I ran by. I saw a look of mild surprise (which was appropriate; who in his right mind would run in this ungodly weather?). He called out: &quot;Hey diehard!&quot; and &quot;Bravo!&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was happy and grateful for this. It did give me a bit more energy. But as welcome and motivational this compliment was, it was incorrect. I am not a diehard. I am merely a very stubborn man.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2014 14:43:50 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2014/08/18/i-m-not-a-diehard-i-am-merely-stubborn</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2014/08/18/i-m-not-a-diehard-i-am-merely-stubborn</guid>
        
        
        <category>random thoughts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aaaannnndddd... We&#39;re Back</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear reader. I&#39;m back. Somewhere back in 2012, I became bored, wanted to refactor, did some tinkering, lost track of time, became a father and BAM! It&#39;s August 2014.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;The new site was built on a lot of interesting stuff, including Bootstrap 3 and nicely compiled LESS files. I kept the old color scheme. It looked nice enough.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At the moment, the site is a bit sparse. I was forced to kick out some old modules and some old content. However, maybe somewhere along the line, it will return.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, there are some issues. I am ironing them out. The design needs some decluttering, some whitespace should either be added or moved out and small screens probably have some issues as well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Bear with me. I promise it will be fun.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://medium.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;medium&lt;/a&gt; for some quality content.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2014 14:23:47 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2014/08/15/aaaannnndddd-we-re-back</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2014/08/15/aaaannnndddd-we-re-back</guid>
        
        
        <category>ramblings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Planescape: Torment, 13-ish years later</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The unthinkable happened: a sequel to my favorite game of all time i&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2012-12-03-chris-avellone-blesses-inxiles-planescape-torment-successor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;s in the works&lt;/a&gt;. My inner geek is squealing with delight. Here. Have some nostalgia.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;Planescape: Torment is a Computer Role Playing Game based on the famed Infinity Engine, which also powered the famous Baldur&#39;s Gate series. It was set in the Planescape universe in the Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons tabletop RPG. When P:T came out late 1999, it received rave reviews, even if it was only single player and the graphics were obsolete. In 1999, it was just not done to release a 2D game. However, the story was intricate to say the least, it had a number of different endings, and it could be played in several ways.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First of all, the game was extremely atmospheric. The fantasy setting was sheer genius, ranging from baroque to victorian with a healthy dose of surrealism. The sound and music were haunting and the graphics both gritty and intricate. In all honesty, the battle system was sometimes somewhat kludgy, but the focus on the game was not hack &amp;amp; slash, but character development.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The best part of the game though was its story and its character development. The main character is called The Nameless One. He wakes up in a morgue and discovers that he remembers absolutely nothing. The game is ultimately about finding out about the history of The Nameless One. During the game, you find several characters. Some of them will join you in your search for the past. Every party member is an enigma, with a back story, that interconnects with the history of the Nameless One. Every now and then, you have to interview them. Dependent on the answers you choose, you find out pieces of the Nameless One&#39;s past, not only gaining experience, but also well, information.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is primarily the sheer complexity of the story that made me play the game twice in a row. In its entirety. You could play the game twice and find out about totally different parts of the Nameless One&#39;s past. Some party members were extremely difficult to find, yet interesting enough to warrant such a long search.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This concept was ambitious, perhaps too ambitious. The script is said to have 800.000 words in it, which is a staggering amount. The game did not sell well. Ultimately, the developer went out of business. Speculations on the reasons of its poor sales range from not being multiplayer to being too complex and too little hack and slash. Whatever the actual reasons, for me Planescape:Torment may be the best computer game I have played, and one of the few that actually deserves a sequel.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2012 08:01:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2012/12/09/planescape-torment,-13-ish-years-later</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2012/12/09/planescape-torment,-13-ish-years-later</guid>
        
        
        <category>ramblings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Linux Desktop </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Currently, there is a raging discussion in the Linux community on the death of the Linux Desktop and who is to blame for it. For years, people have been claiming that the Linux desktop was going to get its breaktrough, but that promise never quite went true.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;In short, Miguel de Icaza, the former lead developer of the Gnome desktop environment, &lt;a href=&quot;http://tirania.org/blog/archive/2012/Aug-29.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;blames&lt;/a&gt; the community&#39;s &#39;developer culture&#39; for the death of the Linux desktop. By innovating for the sake of innovating, and cultivating a hackish culture, Linux missed the big picture, and simply lost the chance of ever making it as a desktop OS. This spawned an interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/115250422803614415116/posts/hMT5kW8LKJk&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;discussion&lt;/a&gt; in which many famous persons in the OSS community have a say.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;IMHO, Gnome 2 has hurt the Linux desktop more than any developer mindset can achieve. That is another rant though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is it a bad thing that the Linux desktop is (apparently) dead? Is it dead at all? Linux is a lot of things. It runs on countless servers, has a hot stepdaughter in the moblie market (and a few ugly ones as well), is an excellent choice for embedded systems, and has even powered coffee machines as early as 1997. Furthermore, it does have a large number of window managers and desktop environments.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing is missing though: it is not a consumer OS. Many attempts have been made to beat the Linux desktop into submission and make it user friendly enough for the masses. The one distro that came closest, is Ubuntu, but they lost the way with their Unity desktop.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The consumer desktop is IMHO a dead horse. First of all, the desktop metaphor is flawed. Everybody uses it, but think about it. What is the similarity between a vertical screen that is your window to the world compared to a horizontal surface that contains your work, and is commonly associated with a TL-illuminated hell? There must be a better way to make the use a computer understandable to a layman.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Add to this that many people want their home computer to exactly look and feel like the one they use at work, and voila, here&#39;s a major reason that Microsoft still dominates the home computer. They make desktops that fit dreary office life perfectly, and it shows in the blandness of their products.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The desktop metaphor is losing ground though. Smartphones and tablets are increasingly used in the homes many people. Why not anyway? Many tasks do not require a physical keyboard, and the point and click interface has been replaced by a more friendly point and tap interface.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The guys at Microsoft are seeing this. Windows 8 abolishes the desktop, replacing it with a more tablet-friendly interface. The flaw in their plan though is that they try to force this paradigm onto desktop PCs as well. Since the tablet is a totally different beast with totally different input methods, this will probably hurt the acceptance of their new OS.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another &#39;desktop&#39; environment that is slowly losing the desktop shackles, is KDE Netbook remix. It is buggy as hell, feels klunky at times and crashes daily on my machine, but the idea is a decent one.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I for one am not certain whether the Linux OS should be a consumer OS. Admittedly, part of it is snobism. I like the &#39;developer culture&#39; that Mr. de Icaza mentions. The user interface has grown though. Both KDE and Gnome have been obsoleted by OSX and even Windows 7. This is a harsh conclusion, but a fair one.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps one should accept the idea that the Linux desktop is not for the masses, nor should it be intended to be. After all, a linux computer still requires a lot of manual tweaking. The desktops as they are serve a good niche. Many developers and hobbyists use and love the linux desktop experience. That does not make them suitable for the masses though, even if they save the users or sysadmins a lot of headaches.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Linux is reaching the masses, if only disguised as its hot stepdaughter. After all, ATM, the&amp;nbsp; the only viable more-or-less-open mobile OS is Android. Maybe this is as it should be. Drop the calcified desktop and go for the sexy new interfaces. Open source is all about moving on.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Sep 2012 19:42:26 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2012/09/04/the-linux-desktop</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2012/09/04/the-linux-desktop</guid>
        
        
        <category>ramblings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Internet Explorer Tax</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;An Australian retailer has started charging users of Internet Explorer 7, since it costs too much to keep supporting said browser. The user can install a decent browser, thus avoiding the IE7 tax on the spot. Is this a good thing or not?&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;Users need to be made aware that using obsolete software is not a good idea for the same reason that you do not drink expired milk. It has gone bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The hours lost on debugging Internet Explorer-specific issues are traditionally many. While most other desktop browsers use more or less the same standards and methodology, Internet Explorer is known by web developers for its um.. quirks. Bluntly put, all versions up to 9 have their own &#39;standard&#39;. These are often poorly documented (if at all), which results in costly work-arounds. The many hours lost by these hacks will have to be compensated for by the customer, who generally has little appreciation for this fact. Many web developers would prefer not to support Internet Explorer at all, but it is still a widely used browser.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A more hateful and frustrated version of me would have said let them bleed.&amp;nbsp;There is a big &lt;em&gt;however&lt;/em&gt; though. It is less than reasonable to penalize people for the software they use. This is a form of vendor lockout. I loathe the vendor, but as an Open Source enthusiast (and wanna-be &amp;nbsp; contributor) I think that this is a bad message.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do not mind chiding people for using piece of shit software, and I will happily pull the plug on old Internet Explorer versions, but charging people extra for using said software is a bridge too far. It reminds me too much of said vendors.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jun 2012 14:52:40 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2012/06/14/internet-explorer-tax</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2012/06/14/internet-explorer-tax</guid>
        
        
        <category>rants</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>No respect for IT skills</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, our minister of internal affairs launched one of her &#39;brain&#39;-farts. Students were to be invited to try to hack government servers and applications. Free of charge. Sadly, this attitude towards IT skills as something that I encounter daily.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;h2&gt;Lack of vision&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the articles &amp;nbsp;that triggered this rant can be read &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nu.nl/column-zaterdag/2760146/beveiligings-carnaval.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;nbsp;The gist is that it may seem a good idea, but only shows our government&#39;s utter incompetence and underestimation of computer security (and IT in general). The best one liner of this column is roughly translated: &#39;Our government knows as much about IT as president Assad of First Aid&#39;. It is quite harsh, but sadly, it is true.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Our government (at least: the political parties who are actually in the Cabinet) has an utter and total lack of vision on IT. They totally misunderstand Intellectual Property in the 21st century, their lack of IT infrastructure -and knowledge- is biting them in the ass, and instead of doing anything about that situation, they are killing our educational system.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;No freebees&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Apart from the rant above, there is a totally different reason why I hate this proposal: this idea is insulting. I have been in this business for over a decade. I am more or less self-educated, and I am making a decent living out of it. Once in a while, somebody asks me for &#39;advice&#39; on an IT-related issue. However, what they actually want, is for me to fix their IT-related problems, &lt;em&gt;without them doing any effort themselves&lt;/em&gt;. &amp;nbsp;Their lame excuse is that they do not understand this computer stuff.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Imagine going to a surgeon for a free operation, a cook for free food or a car mechanic for a free, yet complicated repair. These situations are inconceivable. However, if IT skills are involved, people are trying to freeload. Well, fuck you!&amp;nbsp;I am not doing that. If you do not know how to use something, you either teach yourself, or pay somebody to do it for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;The IT Stigma&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This story irks me for another reason: there is this stigma about being in IT. You automatically get a label that claims that you lack social skills. Granted, there are many colorful, &#39;out-of-the-ordinary&#39; people in IT. However, this does not mean that one in by definition a sociopath because of the career he (or she) chose. We are not monkeys who do free tricks. We work with knowledge and information, and thus play an important, yet underrated part in our society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;(the lack of) Thinking for Oneself&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People&#39;s inability or unwillingness to think for themselves may account for the fact that religious (and populist) political parties still have such a strong voice in our government. Sadly, this mental apathy will continue to haunt us for many years to come.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2012 17:59:27 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2012/03/10/on-respect-for-it-skills</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://derjoachim.nl/blog/2012/03/10/on-respect-for-it-skills</guid>
        
        
        <category>rants</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
